You've never left the battlefield.
您从未离开过战场
"Life or death,"
苟利社稷
"I will do whatever I can for the benefits of the country"
死生以之
If you grasp the implication,
你如果能读懂这句话
you'll understand my choices.
你就会明白我的选择
Dad,
爸爸
I read pieces of news
我刚才看了
from the "Central Daily" today.
今天的《中央日报》
The communists from Sichuan
从四川北上的共产党
have already crossed Huining.
已经过了会宁
After Huining, it's a foregone conclusion.
会宁之后再无悬念
Mr. He said in the meeting
何部长在会上讲
that the Chairman intends to establish
委员长有意在西安
a Northwest Command in Xi'an
设立西北剿共司令部
for the sixth
做好第六次
encirclement campaign against CPC.
围剿的准备吧
Is Hua Zhen done
华桢在上海的事情
in Shanghai?
办完了吗
He said
上回听他说
he'd be back
假期结束之前
by the end of the holidays.
肯定能回来
Is he still questioning
他还在打听
about Deng Mingyuan?
邓铭远的事情吗
No.
没有
What's the matter, Dad?
怎么了爸爸
There's going to be
这两天会有
a party memo about Deng Mingyuan soon.
关于邓铭远的党内通报
If Hua Zhen asks,
华桢如果问起
just play dumb.
你就推说不知道
The Navy Dept.'s confirmed
海军部已经查实
that Deng was convicted of information leak
邓铭远和当年那桩关于
of the anti-communist
围剿共产党的
encirclement campaigns.
泄密案有关
Had not for that leak,
如果不是那次泄密
our fourth attempt
我们第四次围剿
might have succeeded.
或许已经成功了
Instead, here we are,
何至于今日今时
preparing for
连小学生们
the sixth attempt,
都在呐喊申请抗日
while school children
我们却要做
are rallying for resistance against the Japanese.
第六次围剿的准备
I heard
我听说
that the Central Military Prison
中央军人监狱
has already sent someone to Shanghai
已经派人去了上海
to escort Deng back to Nanjing.
要把邓押解回南京
But there's no
但是最后怎么判的
final verdict yet.
还没有正式结果
There is now.
现在已经有了
Mr. He ordered
何部长亲自电令
Shanghai Garrison Command
淞沪警备司令部
to escort him to Nanjing for immediate execution.
押解南京 即刻枪决
Sir, were you looking for me?
先生 是您找我
Hello.
您好
I'm a friend of Mr.
我是孟先生和孟太太的
and Mrs. Meng.
朋友
There's something
有件东西
I need you to
想拜托您
pass on to a young person.
转交给一位年轻人
[Newspapers for sale! Get your newspapers!]
卖报了 卖报卖报
Today, I met my tutor.
今天我见到了我的老师
He said,
他对我说
if I can grasp the meaning of
如果我能读得懂
"Life or death, I will do whatever I can for the benefits of the country",
苟利社稷 死生以之
I will
这句话
understand his decision.
就能明白他的选择
He wouldn't bring it up
他不会无缘无故
without reason.
提到这句话的
Did your tutor
你的老师
know my parents?
认识我的爸爸妈妈
Yes.
对
He's the one who asked me to come to Shanghai
他就是托我来上海
and deliver boat tickets to you.
给你们送船票的人
Are you Mr. Hua Zhen?
请问是华桢华先生吗
That's me.
是我
Please come in.
请进
Mr. Hua,
华先生
a gentleman left a message,
有位先生留了话
insisting that I
让我一定亲手
hand this letter to you personally.
把一封信交给您
Just a moment.
稍等一下啊
Here it is, Mr. Hua.
华先生 就这封信
Who was it?
是什么人
I don't know him.
我也不认识
He only mentioned that
他只是说自己是
he was a friend of Mr. and Mrs. Meng.
孟先生和孟太太的朋友
Ms. Zhang,
张老师张老师
I've finished my writing.
我的字写完了
Please take a look.
你快看我写的
Sure.
好
Excuse me.
失陪啊
[Hua Zhen,]
华桢
[I knew you]
我知道你
[would find this place,]
一定会很快找到这里
[so I've left this letter for you.]
所以给你留了这封信
[I am sorry]
很抱歉
[for the impact]
终究还是
[this has had on your life.]
影响到你的人生
[I owe you]
我欠你
[an explanation for everything.]
对整件事情的解释
[But given my current situation,]
但我想以我现在的处境
[it's unlikely I'll have]
大概没有机会
[the chance to tell you in person.]
亲口告诉你这些了
[I hope this letter]
希望这封信
[clears up any doubts you have.]
能够解开你所有的疑惑
[Five years ago, when the three northeastern provinces fell,]
五年前东北三省沦陷
[national salvation became imperative.]
民族救亡势在必行
[A couple in Shanghai, the Mengs,]
上海一对姓孟的夫妇
[along with]
联合沪上
[dozens of patriotic merchants,]
数十位爱国商人
[formed an alliance]
结成同盟
[to secretly support the resistance war in the north.]
秘密支援北方抗日力量
[Over the years,]
在这之后的几年时间里
[they gave everything,]
他们倾其所有
[not only raising funds and supplies]
不仅为北方战场
[for the northern front]
筹钱筹物
[but also sheltering]
更收留了那些
[children whose parents had perished]
父母在战场上
[on the battlefield.]
牺牲的孩子
[The couple]
那对夫妇
[are Duoci's parents.]
就是多慈的父母
[The funds]
放在汇丰银行
[they collected and stored]
保险柜里的
[in an HSBC Bank safe]
是多慈父母生前
[were their last contribution.]
最后一次筹集的资金
[By the time you read this letter,]
在你看到这封信的时候
[that money]
那笔资金
[should have been working.]
也应该开始运转了
[Have you heard of ISKRA?]
你听说过依斯克拉吗
[In Russian, it means "spark".]
在俄语里它代表星火
[I named the operation]
我给这次行动取名为
[ISKRA]
依斯克拉
[because these children]
因为那些孩子
[are descendants of heroes]
是英雄的后代
[and are the sparks of the future.]
也是未来的星星之火
[I have recorded]
我在联络册上
[the names]
记下了
[of 452 children in the contact book,]
四百五十二个名字
[each of whom lost parents]
都是父母因抗日
[to the war against Japanese intrusion.]
而牺牲的孩子
[Recording]
记录他们
[their details]
每一个人的信息
[is to ensure]
为的是
[they never]
让他们永远
[forget their origins.]
不遗忘自己的身份
[Some protect them,]
有人在保护他们
[some nurture them,]
有人在抚养他们
[and others,]
还有人
[who may never]
从未出现在
[appear in their lives,]
他们成长的路上
[still shape their destinies.]
却在影响他们一生
[Perhaps,]
也许
[more names will be]
将来联络册上
[added to this book in the future.]
还会记下更多的名字
[But as long as the spark endures,]
但只要星火不灭
[there is hope for our nation.]
民族就有希望
[Life or death,]
苟利社稷
[I will do whatever I can for the benefits of the country.]
死生以之
[I hope one day]
愿你终有一天
[you will understand my choices.]
能够明白我的选择
Yuansheng,
远生哥哥
I really
我真的很想
miss my parents.
我的爸爸妈妈
Qiushi,
秋实
your parents,
你的父母
my tutor,
我的老师
and their comrades
还有他们的同志
are all true heroes.
他们都是真正的英雄
Hey,
小妹妹
this star is for you.
这颗星星送给你
Thank you.
谢谢你
You're welcome.
不客气
[We could once hide,]
我们还可暂时躲避
[but not now.]
然而现在可能吗
[Now,]
在现在
[we no longer have]
我们没有机会
[the luxury of ease.]
再悠闲自适的了
[Their sacrifices are worthy.]
他们的牺牲是值得的
The organization
组织派人
has activated Comrade Chen Hao.
和陈浩同志接上了线
He has now
他已经接替您
become the fifth 037.
成为第五位零三七
This code will not disappear.
这个代号不会消失
Operation ISKRA
依斯克拉计划
will continue
也会继续执行下去
until the day
不到胜利的那一天
of victory.
这个计划永远不会中断
That is a promise
这是党
of the CPC and the organization.
和组织的承诺
Eat now, or the noodles will get soggy.
再不吃 面就坨了
Get ready!
准备
What's on your mind?
你想干什么
You go back.
你自己回去吧
I need to stay.
我要留下来
But we've been
但是我们
ordered for extradition.
已经被判引渡了
Without getting the money from the bank
不拿到银行里的那笔钱
and finding that hidden child,
找到那个躲起来的小孩
I won't return.
我不会回去
We've fought before.
我跟你交过手
You're a soldier too,
你也是军人
right?
对不对
If you truly are,
如果你也是军人
then you should understand
你应该清楚
that China's issue
中国的问题
can no longer be resolved peacefully.
已经不可能和平解决
War is the only solution.
战争是唯一的出路
I know you
我知道你们的人
have taken
已经拿走了
the money from the bank.
银行里的那笔钱
Even if you manage to protect those kids,
就算你能保护那些小孩
it's futile.
也没用
Every industrial site
在你们沿海的
along your coast,
每一个工业点
every new railway
通往内陆的
leading inland,
每一条新铁路
all have been
一切都已经
marked on our maps.
被标注在地图上
Once our
只要我们的陆海军
forces start,
开始行动
it will only take
十日之内
ten days to break open your defense.
就可以长驱直入
The kids from the ISKRA,
依斯克拉计划的小孩
we will find them eventually.
我们迟早会找到
Including Meng Duoci,
你救走的孟多慈
none of them will escape.
他们谁也别想逃掉
Extradition is the bottom line.
引渡是最后底线
You shouldn't have left the ship.
你不该下船
Move!
让开
I've told you before,
之前我跟你提过
about my teacher Deng Mingyuan.
我的老师邓铭远
He was executed
今天在
today at
南京中央军人监狱
Nanjing Central Military Prison.
被执行了枪决
Because he was a communist.
因为他是共产党
This is the last letter
这是他留给我的
he left me.
最后一封信
This should put an end to the matter.
这件事应该划上句号了
What are your plans next?
接下来有什么打算
Before coming to Shanghai,
这趟来上海之前
my life
我的人生轨迹
was never influenced by external forces.
从来没有被外力改变过
Thus, I never truly
因此我也从来没有
experienced life itself.
感受到生活本身
Only now do I start to realize,
现在我才渐渐发现
maybe my path has changed.
也许我的轨迹已经变了
Maybe everyone's path
也许所有人的轨迹
is meant to change.
都注定被改变
Who knows?
谁知道呢
Yeah,
是呀
Go home.
回家吧
You've been away too long.
你离开家太久了
Go back.
回去吧
Did you find Takagi?
找到高木君了吗
Found him by the river.
在江边找到了
Shot twice,
身上中了两枪
already dead.
已经身亡
Mr. Feng is looking for witnesses.
冯科长正在寻找目击者
It might
恐怕
take some time.
还需要点时间
Looks like it might turn into a cold case.
恐怕要成为无头案了吧
No worries,
您放心
we'll do everything
我们一定尽全力
to catch the killer.
缉拿凶手
The money in the bank
银行保险柜里的钱
has also been taken.
也已经被人取走了
It's too late.
晚了
The Meng couple and the communists
孟家夫妇和共产党
were doing more
绝不仅仅是
than just feeding
让那些孩子吃饱饭
those kids.
那么简单
The kids you're worried about
您担心的那些孩子啊
are just a few hundred.
其实不过区区几百人
They're still
他们现在
blank slates.
还都是白纸一张
Even in three to five years,
就算是再过个三年五年
they might not pose a threat.
也未必能形成威胁吧
Do you know
知道战争中
what's the most terrifying aspect of war? (in Japanese)
最可怕的是什么吗
It isn't your
不是你们
industrial sites along the coast,
在沿海的工业点
nor the increasing number
也不是越来越多
of railways leading to the inland.
通往内地的铁路
China's real strength
中国的实力
doesn't lie there.
并不全在那里
This land is primal.
这片土地是原始的
Its roots are buried in the soil.
它的根在泥土里
As long as there's rainfall and sunlight,
只要下雨 出太阳
the rice will grow.
稻谷就会生长
That's why this nation
这也是这个民族
is so hard to eradicate.
难以消亡的原因
What do you think
您说 那个里见
Nakamura's attitude towards us really is?
到底对我们是什么态度
You mean his last remarks?
你指他最后那番话
Yeah.
是啊
Crops growing
什么谷物就会生长
and being hard to eradicate?
难以消亡
What does he mean?
他说这些话是什么意思
Is he fighting us
难道一边打
while praising us?
还要一边夸
For someone who harbors ambition
衣兜里只有野心
but lacks morality,
没有道德的人
those words
说这些话
are merely
不过是因为
out of frustration for not being able to
没有三五天灭掉你
annihilate us in a few days.
恨得牙痒痒罢了
If you genuinely think
要是真的以为
he's praising
他在赞美你
or admiring us,
或者敬仰你
that's too naive.
那就太天真了
But we work for the Japanese.
可是我们给日本人做事
Don't we need to foster good relations?
难道不用搞好关系吗
I'm focused on amassing something to bargain with.
我要的是累积资本
As for relations,
关系
mutual respect
能勉强相互尊重
is good.
就够了
Deputy Director,
副局长
I'll just follow your lead.
反正我就跟着你
I prefer not to dwell on those
那些太过复杂的问题
overly complex matters.
我懒得去想
Guangyun, sit down.
广云 坐
Nakamura is clearly
高木环被杀的这件事儿
bothered
看得出来
by Takagi Tamaki's murder.
里见还是很介意
I overlooked
这件事情
that matter.
我确实大意了
But he shouldn't have
可是他也不应该
gone off on his own.
瞒着我们自己下船
Did he really think
他真当自己
he was invincible?
有三头六臂吗
Well,
现在
any clues yet?
还是一点线索都没有吗
I spoke with the harbor patrol.
我问过码头巡警了
Someone heard
有人听见过
gunshots near the warehouse,
仓库方向的枪声
but by the time they arrived,
可是他们赶到的时候
there was no one there.
就没有人了
No witnesses
目前还没有找到目击者
or weapon found yet.
也没有找到凶器
However,
不过
I think the most likely suspect
我觉得可能性最大的
is the person
是跟孟多慈
who stayed in the apartment with Meng Duoci.
一起住在公寓的那个人
I checked the registry.
我看过登记簿
His name is Hua Zhen.
名字叫华桢
What did you say?
叫华什么
Feng Sir,
冯科长冯科长
if you had
你如果早一点
informed me earlier,
告诉我这事儿
it wouldn't have
事情也不至于
escalated to this point.
变成现在这样
I don't follow.
我不太明白您的意思
Stop focusing on Hua Zhen.
别再只盯着华桢了
Direct your efforts
你要把精力
towards the journalist from
放在眼下救国会的
the national salvation organization.
那个记者身上
He shouldn't take
他拍到了
those photos.
不该拍到的照片
This issue
这件事
is trickier than the Meng case.
远比孟家的案子棘手
We have
那个记者
the journalist in custody,
已经在我们手上了
and we've retrieved the photos.
照片也找到了
Just
只不过
haven't got the negatives yet.
暂时还没有拿到底片
He's just a frail journalist.
一个文弱记者而已
You couldn't break him?
你撬不开他的嘴
I've beaten him within an inch of his life
已经打得死去活来
for more than one time.
好几次了
He just won't talk.
他不肯说
I'm afraid of killing him.
我都怕把他给打死
So, I've just detained him.
所以我只能先关着
But he has a wife,
但是他有个老婆
who's likely gone into hiding
现在应该是听到风声
after hearing rumors.
躲起来了
My men are searching for her.
我已经安排人去找了
Don't worry,
您放心
I'll find a way
我总有办法
to get those negatives.
让他交出底片
The Meng case
孟家的事
wasn't dwelt on by Nakamura
里见没有过多计较
because
就是因为
our uniforms
我们身上的这身警服
still hold value.
还有价值
Keep that in mind.
自己心里要有数
As for Hua Zhen,
至于华桢
stop meddling
他的事儿
in his affairs.
你就别再插手了
No more investigation?
那不查了
Not even I
别说你
am not in the position to investigate him.
我也未必能查他
Think of him as Sun Wukong.
你就当他是孙猴子
If you didn't have Buddha
如果没有如来佛
to suppress him
把他压倒在
under the Five Fingers Mountain,
五指山下的本事
stay out of his business.
就别再插手他的事
Otherwise, it's you and me
否则最后倒霉的
who will end up worse off.
还是你和我
You'll understand
这件事儿
this later.
以后你会明白的
And,
另外
that Captain
你手下
from the Fourth House,
四所的那个小队长
what's his name again?
叫 叫什么
Chen Hao.
陈浩
Right, Chen Hao.
对 陈浩
Lift his
他的停职处分
suspension too.
也撤销了吧
Is he also Sun Wukong?
他也是孙猴子
The Police Service of French Concession Municipal Council
公董局警务处
sent a letter of thanks to headquarters,
给总局来了封信
thanking Chen Hao for assisting
感谢陈浩协助他们
in capturing the killer.
抓捕凶手
The Director
局长
also wants to use this opportunity
也想借此机会
to ease
缓解一下
relations with the foreigners.
和洋人之间的关系
From my position,
站在我的位置
I also don't want to complicate things further.
也不想把事情复杂化
Let it rest.
到此为止吧
[Captain,]
队长
[we're approaching Zhang Runjin's]
前面就是张润金
[hideout in Shanghai.]
在上海的藏身处
[Our scouts]
我们的侦查队员
[are already upstairs.]
已经上去了
Any findings?
有什么新发现吗
Sorry, nothing yet.
对不起 还没有
Coming!
来了
Hello,
你好
is this Mr. Zhang Runjin's residence?
请问是张润金的家吗
Yes, he just stepped out.
是 他刚出去
I have a letter for Mr. Zhang.
我这里有张先生的信
Just leave it here.
就搁这儿吧
He'll pick it up soon.
他一会儿会来拿的
Alright.
好嘞
Thank you.
谢谢你啊
Renting a house in Guangzhou?
在广州租房子
Guangzhou?
广州
Take a good look.
你好好看看
Look at this letter
好好看看
to Zhang Runjin.
张润金收到的这封信
The landlord mentions
里面那个房东说
that Zhang rented a house
张润金一个月之前
in Guangzhou a month ago
就在广州租了房子
and paid a year's rent in advance,
还付了一年的租金
but no one
可直到现在
has moved in yet.
都没有人住进去
Are you suggesting
您是怀疑
this house might be connected to Hua Zhen?
这房子和华桢有关
Zhang Runjin wouldn't rent a house in Guangzhou
张润金离开广州
without good reason
这么久了
after being away for so long.
他不会随随便便租房子
Whether it's related to Hua Zhen,
是不是和华桢有关系
I'm not sure.
我不确定
But I'm certain
但我敢确定
it's connected to something
一定跟共产党
the CPC is up to.
要做的事有关
Come in!
进来
Captain,
队长
I've got the tickets to Guangzhou.
去广州的船票买好了
Excellent! Come on.
太好了 走
Let's head to Guangzhou.
我们去趟广州
Why didn't Mr. Zhang come himself?
老张自己怎么没来呀
He's tied up with business in Shanghai
他在上海忙生意
and can't get away.
走不开
He asked me to handle this for him.
这不托我帮他处理一下
He paid me
这里啊
a year's rent here.
他给了我一年的房租
Said it was for a friend.
说是帮朋友租的
But it's been a month
但是都一个月了
and no one has moved in yet.
一直没人来住
Do you know
你知不知道
what's going on?
是怎么回事儿啊
He didn't mention it.
这他倒没说呀
Do you know
您知道他
who he rented it for?
租给什么朋友了吗
Not much.
只知道
It should be for a couple with a child
是一对带孩子的夫妻
and a young man
还有一个
in his twenties,
二十来岁的年轻人
said to be relocating
说是从外地
to Guangzhou from out of town.
过来广州定居
He is a distant relative of mine,
老张是我远房亲戚
so of course, I trust him
那我肯定信他的嘛
and didn't ask further.
就没多问
What's with the lock today?
今天这锁怎么回事儿
There's no rush.
不着急不着急
He told me
老张说啊
there were some items inside
里面有些东西
he needed me to fetch for him.
托我帮他取一下
There you go.
可以了可以了
Come on in. This way.
来 进来进来
Please come in.
请进请进
He hasn't moved in yet
这老张一直没过来住
and I haven't cleaned.
我也没打扫卫生
Sorry for the dust.
这灰有点儿大
I hope you don't mind.
别介意啊
He's got
这老张
quite a nice place here.
住的条件还不错
Indeed.
那是啊
Honestly,
其实啊
once I've received the rent,
我呢收了人家房租
it's not my place to meddle
人家什么时候来住
when they choose to move in.
我也不用多管
But I've had
但是刚好我这里啊
a bit of trouble here recently.
出了一点点状况